<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English remedy, or, Talbor's wonderful secret for cureing of agues and feavers sold by the author Sir Robert Talbor to the Most Christian King, and since his death ordered by His Majesty to be published in French for the benefit of his subjects ; and now translated into English for publick good.</title>
            <author>Blégny, Monsieur de (Nicolas), 1652-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26272</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09407306</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09407306</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43006</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62495)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43006)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1316:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English remedy, or, Talbor's wonderful secret for cureing of agues and feavers sold by the author Sir Robert Talbor to the Most Christian King, and since his death ordered by His Majesty to be published in French for the benefit of his subjects ; and now translated into English for publick good.</title>
                  <author>Blégny, Monsieur de (Nicolas), 1652-1722.</author>
                  <author>Talbor, Robert, Sir, 1642-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Wallis for Jos. Hindmarsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Nicolas de Blégny--NUC pre-1956 imprints, and to Sir Robert Talbor--Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43006:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43006:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ENGLISH REMEDY: OR, <hi>TALBOR</hi>'s WONDERFUL SECRET, FOR CUREING OF Agues and Feavers. SOLD By the Author Sir <hi>Robert Talbor,</hi> to the moſt Chriſtian King, and ſince his Death, ordered by his Majeſty to be Publiſhed in <hi>French,</hi> for the Benefit of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>AND NOW <hi>Tranſlated into Engliſh for Publick Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Wallis,</hi> for <hi>Joſ. Hindmarſh,</hi> at the Black Bull in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:43006:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43006:2"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Pulbiſher of this Book in <hi>French,</hi> who is Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon to the Duke of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans,</hi> and Director of the College of <hi>New Diſcoveries</hi> in Phyſick, gives us an Account, That by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the <hi>French</hi> King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, he had received from the hands of Monſieur <hi>D'Aquin,</hi> his Majeſties chief Phyſician, the Receipts of that <hi>Arcanum</hi> of Sir <hi>Robert Talbor,</hi> which for a long time was ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful
<pb facs="tcp:43006:3"/>both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> in the Curing of all ſorts of Agues; to be by him Publiſhed for the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his Countrey. That it is the ſame which (as he affirms) his Maſter purchaſed at a very dear rate from the Author, I think no man need to doubt; ſince it is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Orders of that King who is ſo jealous of his Glory as not to ſuffer his Name to be abuſed, nor taken in vain by a ſubject; and that the value of it is ſuch as to render it a publick preſent ſuitable to the Grandure of a great Monarch, the general Applauſe that it has obtain'd from the Learnedeſt of the Faculty of Medicine in that Countrey, and the Experience of thouſands who have found the Benefit of it here in <hi>England,</hi> do ſufficiently evince.
<pb facs="tcp:43006:3"/>The truth is, the Publiſher is not wanting to ſet a juſt eſtimate upon the intrinſick worth of the Remedy, and to recommend it to the World as it deſerves; but when he reflects upon it as an effect of the Liberality of his Prince (as indeed it is) he is tranſported into ſuch raptures of Gratitude, that the Praiſes which upon that occaſion he offers to his Majeſty are ſo boundleſs, that little leſs than an Altar and Incenſe, can excuſe them from Flattery: And that is the reaſon why the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor has not Tranſlated the Preface to the Book, ſeeing the humor of too many of this Kingdom is ſo far from flattering, that it hardly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines them to be grateful to the very beſt of Princes, and much leſs to that King.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43006:4"/>
            <p>Nevertheleſs I think no good man will reckon me guilty of flattery to ſay, That the <hi>French</hi> King hath learned of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of Cureing Agues in the natural body; ſo if occaſion happen (which is not impoſſible) he may learn from the prudent Conduct of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> King (if it be not too hard to be imitated) the Royal Secret of ſtopping the Ague-fits of the State, occaſioned by the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of corrupt and ſeditious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors in ſome of the Noble parts, and in the lower region of the Body Politick, and of curing the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per without much Purging and Blood-letting.</p>
            <p>The Book takes well in <hi>France,</hi> and that made the Tranſlator re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it to the Bookſeller, who
<pb facs="tcp:43006:4"/>now publiſhes it for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Benefit of his Countrey; wherein he hopes not to have deſerved ill of the Publick, which on all occaſions he is ready to ſerve. Accept therefore of the Book, Reader, and make uſe of it to thy beſt advantage, the more thou findeſt therein the greater will be the ſatiisfaction and intereſt of the</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Bookſeller.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:43006:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43006:5"/>
            <head>THE ENGLISH REMEDY: OR, <hi>TALBOR</hi>'s WONDERFUL SECRET.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inquina,</hi> or <hi>Kinakina,</hi> is the Bark of an <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Tree, of the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a <hi>Cherry</hi>-Tree, whoſe leaves much reſemble the leaves of a young Oak, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a fruit not unlike to an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn, the figure thereof given by <hi>Johnſtonus</hi> may be ſeen at the end of the <hi>Hiſtory of Trees</hi> written by <hi>Mantiſsa.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43006:6"/>
            <p>It is hardly as yet thirty years ſince this Drug became known in <hi>Europe:</hi> ſince that time many Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors have wrote of it, as <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonus, James Chifflet, Denis Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet,</hi> in his <hi>Royal Garden of Plants; Roland Sturmius, Melipus, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igius, Gaudentius, Brunatius, Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangus, Hoeferus, Willis, Rolfin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> a Phyſitian of <hi>Leyden</hi> that hath added to <hi>Scroderus, M. de Muve,</hi> in his <hi>Pharmaceutick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionary,</hi> the Author of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the <hi>Cure of Feavers,</hi> &amp;c. And laſt of all Mr. <hi>Lemery</hi> in the fourth Edition of his <hi>Courſe of Chymiſtry:</hi> ſeveral other curious Remarks are to be found in our <hi>Journals of Medicine</hi> upon the ſame ſubject.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43006:6"/>
            <p>Theſe Authors do not all agree upon the Etimology of its name, nor upon the place from whence it is brought; for ſome affirm that it comes from <hi>China,</hi> and therefore many have called it <hi>Cortex ſineaſis,</hi> and to diſtinguiſh it from that Root which is called <hi>China</hi> or <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> they have named it <hi>Quinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> or (which is the ſame thing) <hi>Kina-kina:</hi> others again who are more in number, maintain that it is brought from <hi>Peru,</hi> where the Feaver or Ague is called <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> whence comes the name <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina;</hi> That the Natives of that Countrey call it <hi>Gannateride;</hi> that becauſe of its extraction it ought to be called in <hi>Latin, Cortex Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruviana,</hi> and in the vulgar Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage the Bark of <hi>Peru,</hi> and that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43006:7"/>the name of <hi>Jeſuits Powder</hi> by which it commonly goes, was given it, becauſe the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were the firſt that brought it from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> of which <hi>Peru</hi> is a part. However the matter be, they begin now to call it in <hi>Latin, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tex febrilis;</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> name it, <hi>Palo de Culenturas,</hi> i. e. <hi>Feaver-wood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon why it was thought to come from <hi>China,</hi> was becauſe much of it was brought from <hi>Portugal,</hi> but that makes nothing againſt the common opinion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is known that the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueze</hi> have Commerce with both <hi>Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some Authors make two kinds of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> one which they ſay is wild and of little value,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43006:7"/>and another which they think is cultivated, and therefore ſay that it is the better of the two; but to make a true eſtimate of their quality, it were fit one ſhould be upon the place where they grow.</p>
            <p>It is certain nevertheleſs that the goodneſs of it may be known by ſome marks which experience hath diſcovered; for the beſt hath always its upper rind or skin cut tranſverſally or croſsways with pretty deep ſtreaks or lines, and long-ways with very ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ones when it is freſh, and now the moſt part of the little ſquares or interſtices of its skin, are of a ſilver white colour; it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways of a clear reddiſh colour, compact, very bitter, and gives to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43006:8"/>the boxes wherein it is kept a ſweet and pleaſant ſmell.</p>
            <p>But it is to be obſerved that that ſmell is much weaker and leſs aromatick than the ſcent of <hi>Caſſia Cariophilata,</hi> which by cheats is Sold for <hi>Quinquina,</hi> min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling it with the bark of <hi>Cherry</hi>-Tree, which for ſome days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have ſteept in Water wherein <hi>Aloes</hi> hath been diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and this is a very culpable ſophiſtication, ſeeing theſe kinds of barks have nothing of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of <hi>Quinquina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is beſides this, another way of cheating the Publick as to the matter of the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> for there are ſome <hi>Droguiſts</hi> that infuſe it entire, and having by that means extracted the firſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43006:8"/>
               <hi>Tincture</hi> out of it, for their own advantage, ſell it afterward at the ſame rate as if it had not loſt his chief virtue.</p>
            <p>Hitherto the price of <hi>Quinquina</hi> or <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> hath been very various and uncertain. When it was only in the hands of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi> it was ſold at <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> for <hi>Eight</hi> or <hi>Nine</hi> Shillings <hi>Sterling</hi> the <hi>Doſe,</hi> which conſiſted only of <hi>Two Drachms;</hi> but ſo ſoon as <hi>Droguiſts</hi> began to Trade in it, it began to fall in Price, ſo that <hi>Three</hi> or <hi>Four</hi> Years ago, the beſt might have been had for about <hi>Forty</hi> Shillings the Pound weight; but no ſooner began the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Remedy to be in vogue, but men began every where to make Experiments with the Bark
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43006:9"/>of <hi>Peru,</hi> which much enhanſed the value of it: yet that was not all which raiſed it to the higheſt price; for Sir <hi>Robert Talbot</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that <hi>Febrifuges</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd which came very near his own, and fearing leaſt ſome body at length might diſcover it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to buy up all the <hi>Quinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> that he could find at <hi>Paris,</hi> and the other chief Towns of <hi>France,</hi> and of <hi>England</hi> alſo. The execution of this Deſign making ſome noiſe, ſeveral <hi>Phyſitians, Chirurgeons</hi> and <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> thought it concerned them, to make all haſt to provide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and ſome that they might not be wanting in Precaution, cauſed a conſiderable quantity of the Bark to be brought from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43006:9"/>
               <hi>Roan</hi> and <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> ſo that Mr. <hi>Audry</hi> and Mr. <hi>Vilain,</hi> the two moſt famous <hi>Droguiſts</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> having Sold all they had at the Rate of about <hi>Fifteen</hi> Pound the pound-weight; and not being able to procure any more from any place, for above a <hi>Fortnight</hi> there was not a bit to be had at any <hi>Droguiſt</hi>'s ſhop in <hi>Paris,</hi> nevertheleſs ſome ſmall quantity came at length, but it was held up ſo dear, that it was like to have gone off at the rate of an <hi>Hundred</hi> Crowns the pound-weight: ſince that time the Merchants having im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported much from <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy having loſt the Advantages of the <hi>Mode;</hi> the price of that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43006:10"/>Commodity hath fallen daily, in ſo much that at preſent it does not yield above <hi>Four</hi> or <hi>Five</hi> Pound the pound-weight; and I make no doubt, but that in a ſhort time a Fleet from the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> will make it much cheaper.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the Authors whom I have named, there are ſome who endeavouring to explain the properties of <hi>Quinquina</hi> or the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> according to the principles of the ancient Medicine, think it enough to ſay that it is hot and dry in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the <hi>Second Degree:</hi> and ſome others of the number of thoſe who have introduced bad Principles into the <hi>New-Philoſophy,</hi> think to mend the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43006:10"/>matter by ſaying, <hi>That</hi> Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina <hi>as an</hi> Alkali <hi>ſtops the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the acid which occaſions the Feaver:</hi> but that is to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate one obſcurity by others that are far more obſcure.</p>
            <p>That we may give the World ſomewhat more ſatisfactory as to that point, we muſt in the firſt place, (with <hi>Willis,</hi>) take our meaſures from <hi>Experience,</hi> and allow with him, That all things which are actually bitter, have great virtue in ſifting pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural fermentations; and upon that account it was that the Root of <hi>Gentian</hi> was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in ſo great reputation for curing of <hi>Quartan Agues;</hi> and that the Flowers of the leſſer <hi>Cantaury,</hi> the Root of <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yerva,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43006:11"/>and <hi>Serpentaria,</hi> the leaves of <hi>Wormwood</hi> and <hi>Chervil, Scam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> and many other bitter <hi>Drogues,</hi> are really <hi>Febrifuges,</hi> though in virtue far inferior to the <hi>Jeſuits Powder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having laid down this from undoubted Truth, we muſt now enquire into the <hi>Natural Cauſes</hi> which produce Bitterneſs in mixt bodies: now ſuppoſing (as it is reaſonable we ſhould) that the true Elements of Bodies are acid, liquid, fiery, etherean, and terreſtrial corpuſcles; it will be a very eaſie matter to diſcover thoſe <hi>Cauſes:</hi> for ſeeing all bitter things penetrate the Tongue, in ſuch a manner that they leave therein a ſenſe of their action for a long time after, and that of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43006:11"/>all the elements none are ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as acids to produce that effect, we muſt conclude that they are predominant in mixts which have that taſt; but alſo ſince being mingled with many liquid corpuſcles, they produce only ſharp and corroding liquors, as the ſpirits of <hi>Salt, Vitriol, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> &amp;c. that being joyned to fiery corpuſcles, they make only <hi>Cauſticks,</hi> as <hi>corroſive ſublimat;</hi> the ſpirit of <hi>Nitre, cauteres,</hi> &amp;c. and that being in intimate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with <hi>Sulphurous</hi> and <hi>Oily</hi> Particles, they only produce ſweet mixts, as <hi>Honey, Sugar,</hi> &amp;c. It follows that none but terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial corpuſcles mingled with them in a proportionable quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, can produce a bitter taſt,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43006:12"/>and in effect the more of <hi>Earth</hi> there is in <hi>Salt,</hi> the bitterer it is, and on the contrary, the more it is refined and depurated, the leſs bitter it is: thus <hi>Sea Salt</hi> diſſolved in a moiſt <hi>Air,</hi> and afterward filtrated through brown paper, has no other taſt than of an acid ſpirit, though before that diſſolution and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration it was conſiderably bitter.</p>
            <p>Now ſince among the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that I have named, the acid is heavieſt, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence the coldeſt; and that though the terreſtrial be not ſo heavy as it, nor yet as the liquid, yet it is more ponderous than the fiery and ethereal, we may ſay that it is temperat; I mean, of a quality equally diſtant from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43006:12"/>the two extreams, and that ſo, being with the acid predominant in a mixt body, the mixt muſt certainly be cooling, or at leaſt proper to preſerve the juſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament of our body.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there are no bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things made up ſolely of acid and terreſtrial corpuſcles, and that there are ſome wherein ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fiery, the ethereal or liquid particles are likewiſe in a conſiderable quantity; ſo there are ſome more or leſs bitter, and even more or leſs cooling and temperate; but if we mind the dryneſs of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> and yet how unapt it is to take fire, it will not be hard to conclude, That the three Elements which I have named laſt, enter but in a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43006:13"/>very ſmall quantity into the compoſition thereof, and that by conſequence amongſt all bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tter mixts none can be of a more temperate quality than it.</p>
            <p>From the Principle which I have now laid down concerning the nature of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> all the other properties thereof may be deduced; for ſeeing its predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant parts are the acids, whoſe property is to coagulate the more ſubſtantial liquors, ſuch as <hi>Blood, Milk,</hi> &amp;c. and the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial which by abſorbing the humidity and unctuoſity that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxates the ſolid parts, does bind and ſtrengthen them; of neceſſity it muſt be ſtiptick and aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and it is in effect in theſe two qualities principally, that the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43006:13"/>rarity and wonderfulneſs of its operation does conſiſt, as I have made appear in former obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p>But it is not to be thought as ſome have imagined, that this property of binding renders it ſo fixative as to keep within the febrifick matter, or other morbifick cauſes diſperſed in the humours, or adhering to the ſolid parts; it is ſo far from that, that by reviting the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenious parts of the blood, it ſeperates them from the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogenious or ſuperabundant parts, whereby it facilitates their expulſion, for which Nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone does often labour in vain, in the ſame manner as by ſtrengthning and fortifying
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43006:14"/>the <hi>viſcera,</hi> it puts them in a condition of reſiſting all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks, and of diſcharging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the Impurties that oppreſs them.</p>
            <p>Experience well agrees with theſe remarks, for the heat that dries up and conſumes the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticks is often extinguiſhed by the uſe of ſeveral Preparations of the Jeſuites Powder. It is no leſs powerful againſt all other internal <hi>Inflammations, Feavers,</hi> and generally againſt all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary and preternatural Fermentations; in a very ſhort time it rectifies the depraved motion and the altered conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtency of the maſs of Blood, and it many times occaſions ſuch
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43006:14"/>ſalutary evacuations, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving dreined the ſourſe of <hi>Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> by the depuration of the natural voices, which through their depravation and tranſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation were become the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent cauſe of it, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the principal cauſe of the expulſion of the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſated Superfluities which were the conjunct cauſe of the ſame.</p>
            <p>It is nevertheleſs ſtrange, that among ſo many Authors, who with admiration have written of its effects, not ſo much as one have taken the pains to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain them by their true cauſes, nor indeed thought that it could be done; for <hi>Willis,</hi> who without doubt hath ſpoken
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43006:15"/>moſt judiciouſly on that ſubject limits himſelf to this, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never ſeen any other ſuch like effects, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to ground a general concluſion upon a particular experiment, all that is to be done is to endeavour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and well obſerve the <hi>phoenomina</hi> that depends there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without troubling ones ſelf with the efficient principles thereof.</p>
            <p>But to make appear how far one may err in the explication of things, when they are not known by their proper cauſes, it will not be amiſs here to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late ſome opinions of that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor touching the effects of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43006:15"/>Jeſuits Powder upon the maſs of Blood: The firſt is that it always cauſes therein a certain Fermentation that only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrovs, that of the Feaver be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it proceeds from another cauſe: Now the Jeſuites Powder does indeed ſift the fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Blood and the other Humonrs, but not excite any it ſelf: The Second is, that it maintains its effect no longer than it is in the Veſſels, and that ſo ſoon as all the parts thereof are ſpent and gone, the diſpoſition that it had ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed infallibly wears, in ſo much that the Relapſe is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain as the ſtopping of the Fit: Nevertheleſs, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43006:16"/>appears daily almoſt, to any who knows how to uſe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: to be ſhort, the Third is, that it ſtops not the Fits of the Feaver, neither by fixing nor yet by reſolving the Blood as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther febrifuges do; nevertheleſs it is certainly true that the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal effect of bitter, aſtringent and ſtiptick februifuges is, the reuniting of the proper parts of the blood divided and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the diſordered Animal Spirits, or by Heterogenious and ſuperfluous matters.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to <hi>Scroderus</hi> has had no better luck, in ſaying that <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina,</hi> or the Jeſuites Powder cures the Feaver by the virtue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43006:16"/>that it hath in Precipitating the Fabrick Ferment, for beſides that it is hard to be underſtood how a matter contained within Veſſels, and mingled with the Blood, can be Precipitated by a Medicine whoſe principal action is directly oppoſite to that of evacuatives; thoſe kinds of Precipitations being only to be made by Urines, by little and little, and in a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpace of time, cannot ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally be attributed to the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites Powder, that acts ſo powerfully, and ſo ſuddenly produces its effect, that many times a ſingle Doſe of it, ſtops and prevents the immediately approaching fit of an Ague.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Cure of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43006:17"/>Feavers and Agues by <hi>Quinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> who makes the cauſe of the Feaver to conſiſt in a certain Acide Ferment, refers the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of that Medicine to the faculty that it hath of ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mortifying, and reſolving that Poiſon; but that Author hath not minded, that if in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Quinquina</hi> were able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy or even to expel the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides that are in the blood, it would not be taken without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely perverting that Liquor, ſeeing it would deaden or drive out the very Acides that make naturally a part of the ſame, and that it muſt neceſſarily loſe its form and be changed into another kind of juyce, if the greateſt part of one or the other
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43006:17"/>of its Elementary principles were taken from it.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Lame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> in his new courſe of Chymiſtry is not ſo wide of the Truth, when he ſays that <hi>Quinquina</hi> does fix and coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Feaveriſh Humor, much in the ſame manner as an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cali</hi> ſifts the motion of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide Salt; for in effect it is the property of that remedy, to rally, bring together, and rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the parts of the liquid body wherewith it is mingled, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as it is put in action by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary diſpoſitions; but that Author hath omited to take notice that this reunion is only made of the proper parts of the blood, and that the Febrifick matter remains confounded in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43006:18"/>the ſuperfluous Seroſity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is evacuated, either by Tranſpiration or by the way of Urine.</p>
            <p>The Principle that I have E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed is of another Nature than the Opinions which I have now related; it is plain, clear, juſt, and every way conforms to all the Experiments that have hitherto been made upon the Jeſuits Powder, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell but that I may ſay to all that ſhall be made hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for whether it be given for our ſort of Feavers, or for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for Vapours (againſt which I take it to be very good) for Dropſies, or for other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, whether it be given in Subſtance, Infuſion, Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43006:18"/>Opiat, Extract, or Quinteſſence: I am perſuaded that its pincipal effect will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be to ſeparate the proper and Homogenious parts of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors from thoſe that are He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous and of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Nature to them, to reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the one, and by that reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to facilitate the expulſion of the others, yet with this difference, that that effect will be more or leſs conſiderable, according to the good or bad uſe and Adminiſtration that ſhall be made thereof.</p>
            <p>Moreover, That we may not too ſlightly paſs over the different <hi>Preparations</hi> that may be made of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> I am not to omit that <hi>Pol Fincius</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:43006:19"/>deſcribes a kind of Eſſence of it, which is nothing elſe but its Tincture Extracted with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Wine, and afterward gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlely evaporated: That <hi>Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> makes a deſcription of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother much like to it, that the Author of the Cure of Feavers by <hi>Quinquina,</hi> will have it to be given in <hi>Bolus</hi> Extract, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented Liquors, and in Infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made in Wine, Ale, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled Waters, Tiſance, and in common water, that Mr. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery</hi> gives the Preparations of a Tincture, of an Extract, and of a Salt of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> that there are other ways of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it to be found in ſeveral Authors which I think needleſs,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43006:19"/>to cite, and that after all the more ſimple and leſs artificial of all theſe preparations are the beſt, as will appear in the deſcription of the <hi>Engliſh Remedy;</hi> which being to be preferred to all that have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been prepared with <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina,</hi> ought to ſerve us as a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, untill we have diſcovered ſome more Excellent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is an Error in Phyſick to make a hodge-podge of a great many ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients (though they be much of the ſame efficace) to ſatisfie one and the ſame indication; and therefore as</hi> Quinquina <hi>or the Bark of</hi> Peru, <hi>whereof I have now given you the Hiſtory, is without contradiction the ſureſt of all ſimple</hi> Febrifuges, <hi>ſo is it the only baſis of the</hi> Engliſh Remedy, <hi>and it will even appear
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43006:20"/>by the following deſcription, that of the Phyſitians, Chyrurgeons, and Apothecaries, that have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to imitate it, thoſe who have prepared it moſt ſimply, have come the neareſt to it, and hereby it is evident that that Author who boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted every where that he had found it out, was very far from it, ſince he always immagined that the virtue of</hi> Quinquina <hi>might be improved by fermenttaion, and by the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the flowers and ſalt of leſſer</hi> Centaury, White Tartar, Sal-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack, Saſſafras-wood, Juniper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, <hi>and ſome other ingredients.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To conclude, though that Remedy conſiſts in ſeveral different prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, yet ſtill they refer indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently to the principle of ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that I have mentioned; and this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43006:20"/>will better appear in the Receipts of them, that Sir</hi> Kobert Talbor <hi>gave the King, and which are here tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed with all the exactneſs that the matter requires.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The firſt infuſion of</hi> Quinquina, <hi>or the</hi> Jeſuits Powder <hi>making a part of the</hi> Engliſh Remedy.</head>
               <p>TAke a pound of the beſt bark of <hi>Quinquina</hi> beaten to a ſubtil powder and ſearced, beſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle it interchangably for the ſpace of a day or two with the decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Anis</hi> and the juice of <hi>Parſley,</hi> then put the powder into an Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Pitcher holding about fifteen or ſixteen quarts, pour upon it gently and ſtill ſtirring the matter, aſmuch good Claret Wine as the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43006:21"/>Veſſel will hold, and having after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtopt it well, let your mixture infuſe for the ſpace of eight days without ſetting it near the fire, but not forgeting to ſtir it two or three times a day with a ſtick or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fit to ſtir the bottom, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward having poured off your liquor, through a cloſe ſtrainer, put it into glaſs bottles, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well ſtopt and placed in a dry place not too Airy, will preſerve it in full force and virtue two or three months and more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Directions given by the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King's Chief Phyſitian, concerning the uſe of this firſt infuſion.</head>
               <p>This firſt infuſion, which is the ſtrongeſt and bittereſt, is to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſtop the fits of an Ague or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43006:21"/>Feaver that one would Cure, the Doſe of it for thoſe of Age and ſtrong perſons, is five or ſix oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that is about half an <hi>Engliſh</hi> pint; but for thoſe who are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally delicate, of a hot conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or not much accuſtomed to Wine, this Doſe ought to be a fourth part leſs, a third part, yea and ſometimes one half leſs, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to correct each Doſe with the addition of a little of the juice of a Lemon or an Orange, when there is no conſideration that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from chooſing the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time to give the firſt Doſe of that infuſion, it ought always to be at the end of a Fit, but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Quartan Agues</hi> that choice might retard the Cure for three or four days, in that caſe it may
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43006:22"/>be uſefully given the night before the next fit that is expected; but then it is good to fortifie each Doſe, by ſome drops of the Eſſence or Tincture whereof we ſhall ſpeak hereafter.</p>
               <p>After one hath began to give of this infuſion, he muſt continue to make the Patient take it once every three hours untill the time of the next fit, unleſs in time of ſleep, which ought never to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, and renew again the uſe of it in the beginning of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, but with this obſervation, that after the Patient hath miſſed one Fit, it will be enough to give a Doſe in the morning faſting, and another a long time after Supper; which is only to be be continued for five or ſix days.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:43006:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſecond infuſion of</hi> Quinquina, <hi>making part of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the ſetlings or remainder of the former infuſion, put it into the ſame Earthen Pitcher, or into another of the ſame bigneſs, with half a pound of freſh <hi>Jeſuits Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> prepared as hath been ſaid, fill the Pot with the ſame Wine, and obſerve in general, as well for the preparation as the preſervation of that ſecond infuſion, all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances directed for the firſt, with this difference only, that for the making of this, ten days are to be employed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43006:23"/>
               <head>Directions given by the King's Chief Phyſitian, concerning the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of this ſecond infuſion.</head>
               <p>When after the Feaver hath ceaſed, the firſt infuſion hath been given morning and evening for the ſpace of ſix days, the uſe of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is to be begun and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Eight days, obſerving the ſame Doſe as of the firſt, but only once a day in the morning when the Patient awakes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The third infuſion of</hi> Quinquina, <hi>making part of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take the ſettlings of the ſecond infuſion, and without any additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on put it again into the ſame
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43006:23"/>Pitcher with the ſame quantity of Wine, and having let it ſtand in infuſion for the ſpace of ten days, and obſerved the directions preſcribed for the preparation and preſervation of the two former infuſions, keep it for the uſe hereafter mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Directions given by the Kings chief Phyſitian concerning the uſe of the third Infuſion.</head>
               <p>The eight days preſeribed for the uſe of the ſecond Infuſion being expired, we muſt begin with the third, which is then ſufficiently ſtrong. It is not to be given for the firſt fortnight but in one Doſe every other day, and then to deſiſt by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43006:24"/>that is, for the next fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night to reduce it to a Doſe once every third day, and ſo to continue until the Patient hath taken of all the three Infuſions about eight quarts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Eſſence or Tincture of</hi> Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina, <hi>making part of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Remedy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take two Ounces of <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina,</hi> Pulveriſed, ſearched and then Alkolized upon a Marble Stone, put it into a Glaſs Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and pour upon it eight Ounces of the beſt Spirit of Wine, ſet your Bottle in the Sun for the ſpace of fifteen days, taking care to ſtir and ſhake it well at leaſt once a day, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43006:24"/>pour off your Tincture, and keep it in a Bottle cloſely ſtopt, to be uſed as occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Directions given by the Kings chief Phyſician; concerning the uſe of the Eſſence or Tincture of</hi> Quinquina.</head>
               <p>Beſides what hath been ſaid touching the uſe of this Eſſence or Tincture, when we ſpake of the time of giving the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, it is ſtill to be obſerved that the virtue of each Doſe of that infuſion is to be encreaſed and fortified by the addition of five, ſix or even ſeven or eight drops of this Tincture, as often as the contumacy of the Ague
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43006:25"/>hath reſiſted its operation after ſeveral Doſes; but this addition is to be regulated by a skilful Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, who is to take his indicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the nature of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and the diſpoſitions of the ſubject.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An Opiat prepared with</hi> Quinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, <hi>making part of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Remedy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take what quantity you pleaſe of <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> prepared as is above directed, and incorporate it with a ſufficient quantity of the ſyrup of Lemons, or of Grimes if it be for a Woman with Child; reducing all into the conſiſtencie of an Opiat by an exact mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:43006:25"/>
               <head>Directions given by the Kings Chief Phyſician, concerning the uſe of the Opiat.</head>
               <p>There are ſome Patients up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom the firſt infuſion though fortified by the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Eſſence or Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture has not ſufficient virtue to ſtop the Ague fits; to theſe the ſpecifick is to be given in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the beſt and moſt commodious way of doing it, is the Opiat that is now deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, it may be given from four to ſix Drachms, once or twice a day according as need ſhall require, and that either upon the point of a Knife, in a Wafer, or in what other manner one pleaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:43006:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Purging Wine making part of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Remedy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take an Ounce of good <hi>Hiera Pica,</hi> and infuſe it for the ſpace of eight days in half a Pint or a little more of Claret wine, obſerving to ſtir the bottle wherein you have put it, only once a day for the firſt three days, and not at all to move or ſhake it during the other five, afterward pour out your infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion gently by inclining the bottle, into another bottle which is to be cloſely ſtopped, and keep it for the uſe follwing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:43006:26"/>
               <head>Directions given by the Kings Chief Phyſitian, concerning the uſe of this Purging-Wine.</head>
               <p>When by reaſon of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents repletion, or a ſupervement conſtipation the belly muſt be opened, we muſt add to each quart of the infuſion of <hi>Quinquina</hi> three or four ſpoonfuls of the above-deſcribed Purging-Wine, ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all exactly together, and uſe it in the ſame manner as hath been directed when we ſpoke of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, that is to ſay, in a greater or ſmaller quantity, according as it ſhall happen in the time of the firſt, ſecond, or third infuſion, and alſo according to the indications taken from the preſent ſtate of the Patient, and of the Diſeaſe.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:43006:27"/>
               <p>It is obſerved that when there is no conſiderable repletion, and that the coſtiveneſs is but mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſimple glyſters made of Milk and the yoalks of Eggs, are to be preferred before all kinds of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives, too great a looſneſs of the belly being always contrary to the operation of the ſpecifick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Other Directions given by the Kings Chief Phyſitian, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is to be obſerved during the courſe of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Remedy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>As it is ſometimes uſeful to open the belly during the uſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Remedy, ſo at other times it is of great importance to ſtop it when by a preceding or ſuperve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient looſneſs, the digeſtion is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43006:27"/>weakened, and the chyle rendred impure; for ſuch diſpoſitions are very much contrary to the Cure of Agues: in ſuch a caſe it is neceſſary that beſides the Doſes of the ſpecifick that are given every day, there be at leaſt two given mingled with an equal part of the tincture of Roſes, extracted upon hot embers with common water, and without the addition of the ſpirit of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> or any other acid ſpirit; for that effect an ounce of red Roſes is ſufficient for a quart of water: this tincture is extracted in twenty four hours, and after it is poured off, three ounces of good white Sugar is to be added to each quart.</p>
               <p>In time of the intermiſſion of the Fits, and as much as may be at the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43006:28"/>uſual hours of eating, the Patients may feed upon what their appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite enclines them to, and chooſe ſuch food as Nature ſeems to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, without any reſervation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be of ſalt Pork and Bacon, yet ſtill obſerving to prefer ſolid food before liquid, and in caſe of thirſt or hunger, not to drink un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till a quarter of an hour, and not to eat till an hour after each Doſe of the <hi>Specifick,</hi> that the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution and digeſtion that ought to be made thereof be not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</p>
               <p>It is moreover to be obſerved, that water and tizanne or barley-water do weaken the virtue of the remedy, and that ſo, Wine and Water, Beer or Ale, ſuch as men drink when they are in health is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43006:28"/>to be preferred before all other Bevrage. Furthermore, ſeeing the operation of the <hi>Specifick</hi> tends always to the recovery of ſtrength, and that other remedies do neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily diminiſh it, they cannot be uſed both at a time, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting many ſalutary opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and without expoſing the Patients to an almoſt certain dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and eſpecially thoſe who by their proper Conſtitution, by Age or the Contumacy of the Diſeaſe, are already much weakened and extenuated; and therefore, as we have juſt now obſerved, the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Remedy cannot be more efficaciouſly aſſiſted than by the uſe of the moſt nouriſhing meats, becauſe they concur with it to the reparation of ſtrength,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43006:29"/>and put the Patients in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of enjoying perfect health ſo ſoon as the Ague is ſtopt.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs a prudent Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian who intends to give the <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificker</hi> may ſometimes by Blood-letting, Purging, and other ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Medicins, correct the bad diſpoſitions of the body, that might hinder the benefit which is to be expected from it; but theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies being only to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as ſimple preparatives, they are always to be uſed before the <hi>Specifick,</hi> which is never more powerful than when it is given by its ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:43006:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Other Obſervations of the Kings chief Phyſician, concerning the Virtues of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Remedy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Never did Remedy better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the name of a ſpecifick Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brifuge; for never did any as yet come to our knowledg, that hath ſo ſpeedily and ſecurely ſtopt, and cured Feavers and Agues, as that hath done. The truth is, <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quind,</hi> which maketh the baſis of it, and which we have had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of for about thirty years, does almoſt infallibly ſtop the fits of Intermittent Feavers, when it is given in ſubſtance in white, ſome without other ceremony; that is to ſay, according to the method Preſcribed by the Jeſuits, who
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43006:30"/>were the firſt that brought that Bark into <hi>Europe;</hi> And in Authors that have written ſince that time ſome other preparations are to be found which are believed to be more efficacious; but experience hath convinced us, that theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors had not as yet found out the ſecureſt method to prevent thoſe troubleſome relapſes, which to this preſent rendered that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy contemptible, and we muſt confeſs that we are in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner obliged to Sir <hi>Robert Talbor,</hi> for having given us a Preparation much to be preferred before all others, whether he hath been the inventer of it, or that he hath hit upon it by chance; and it may be ſaid, that his boldneſs (which would have been taken for a cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43006:30"/>raſhneſs in any but an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick) hath not a little contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the knowledg which we have at preſent of its uſe and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of application.</p>
               <p>The moſt wonderful effects of this Febrifuge appears in all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termittent Feavers, which are its true object; for it ſtops, and in fine wholly Cures Quotidian Agues, Tertian, double Tertian, Quartans, double and tripple Quartans, and ſometimes alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinds of Feavers; for there are ſome continued Feavers, which having kinds of Intermiſſions and Regular Paroxyſms obſervable by ſome ſmall cold in the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Body, or ſome horror and ſhivering betwixt the Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, are cured by the ſpecifick,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43006:31"/>almoſt as ſpeedily and ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the true Intermittent Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; and this happens often in reſpect of ſlow Hectick Feavers accompanied with a Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuch as Children are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly affected with, becauſe they have certain inequalities of remiſſion and augmentation which give ground to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to exert its virtue to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond the attempts of Nature, and by conſequence to reduce the blood unto its former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and to reſtore the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach to its Natural ſtrength, ſo that for the future providing only good and well digeſted Chyle, it ſends a Vivifying hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity to all the parts, which corrects their dryneſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43006:31"/>the loſt Plumpneſs and good habit of body.</p>
               <p>It is nevertheleſs to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that ſince the matter of continued Feavers is diffuſed through the whole maſs of blood, that herein it cauſes a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption hard to be rectified, and that it wholly takes up Nature without giving her any reſpite, ſhe cannot be in a condition to concur the with Specifick, but till by blood letting and Purging, the impure and Heterogeneous matter be in ſome manner ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed, the irritation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins calmed, and the humours be in good enough temper to return into favour with Nature, without which the Specifick, which does not always excite
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43006:32"/>regular Evacuations, is not powerful enough to put a ſtop to the ſedition, and compoſe the diſorder, which is then in the great Veſſels, and in all the other principle and more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary parts of the body.</p>
               <p>For the better underſtanding of the abovementioned directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and obſervations, I would have it remarked, That every thing that occaſions an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary agitation in the ſpirits, humors, and generally in the liquid and fluid parts of our body, may be conſidered as the primitive cauſe of Feavers, that is to ſay, of thoſe irregular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which happen ſo often in the maſs of blood, but ſeems the ſame motions would be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43006:32"/>quickly rectified by Nature, were they not kept in being by ſome permanent cauſe, and that beſides, by diſcompoſing all the oeconomy of Nature, they corrupt the Ferments that ſerve for Digeſtion, and by that means render the Chyle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, and of a bad quality; the depraved Chylification may be looked upon as the immediate and antecedent cauſe of Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; ſo that a Remedy cannot truly be a Febrifuge, unleſs all at once it correct both the bad diſpoſition of Stomach, and of the Ferments, of which I have been ſpeaking, and that is the proper effect of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Febrifuge, for like the moſt part of bitter Medicaments, it is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:43006:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>very Stomachical, being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to conſume the ſuperfluous humidities, and to reſtore the bone of the relaxated Fibres of the Ventricle, and by that means to encreaſe the diminiſhed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, and retrive it when it is wholely loſt, from whence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends the perfect digeſtion of the Victuals, even of the moſt ſolid Food; I cannot tell if one may not affirm it to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo more Cordial: for beſides, that it re-eſtabliſhes the ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forces of the Body, and the decayed natural heat, it fixes the heterogeneous Particles that cauſe the Fermentation of the Blood, and rallies and calls together thoſe which have been divided and ſcattered during its ebullition.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:43006:33"/>
               <p>This Augmentation of force and heat makes it ſometimes appear as if this Febrifuge did re-kindle the Feaver after the taking of the firſt Doſe; but it only augments it that it may the better engage with it, and that apparent diſorder is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſign of its triumph: for the more violent it renders one fit, the more we may be aſſured that it will not be followed by another.</p>
               <p>Many Phyſicians cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how this Remedy which ſeems onely to be fixative, can radically cure Feavers and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues (but it is to be obſerved that though it cauſes not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a ſenſible evacuation, yet it ſo powerful ſeconds the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:43006:34"/>of nature, that during its operation the heterogenious, impure or ſuperfluous matters, are moſt commonly forced out to the ſuperfice of the body, to be evacuated by inſenſible tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, and even very often by copious ſweats, as alſo it is ſometime the occaſion of a cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical looſeneſs of the belly, and in many Patients, the way of the urine ſerves for ſo ſalutary an evacuation, that it cures both together, the Quartan Ague and the Dropſie occaſioned by it.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, though the moſt certain and regular ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Remedy, be to ſtop the fits of intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Feavers, yet the uſe of it is not to be thought of dangerous
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43006:34"/>conſequence; it cauſes no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the oeconomy of Nature, being like other bitter tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate medicaments, incapable of making any bad impreſſion on mans body, for the reunion that it makes of the parts of the blood, always facilitates the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of morbifick Cauſes, and though they ſhould partly ſtay within after its operation; yet by means of it they are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and reconciled to nature, or at leaſt by reiterated and continual digeſtions, they are at length concocted, ripened and diſſipated,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:43006:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Obſervations of the Kings chief Phyſician, concerning the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Sir</hi> Robert Talbor, in the prepation and diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Remedy.</head>
               <p>The greateſt ſecret of moſt of Empiricks, conſiſts only in diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the the Drugs that they make uſe of; for ſince they are the very ſame whereof Phyſicians know the Nature and Properties, they could not make them paſs for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Remedies, unleſs they affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctedly gave them an air of novelty; thus did Sir <hi>Robert Talbor</hi> in the preparation of the Jeſuits Powder, either to make it be believed that the virtue of his Febrifuge did not depend on that Book, or to make
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:43006:35"/>it be thought that he underſtood it much better than thoſe that had made uſe of it before him; for it was very ordinary with him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkle fix Drachms of Red Roſes with two Ounces of the juice of Lemons; and afterward to infuſe them for the ſpace of four hours in ſix Pound of Fountain water, to make uſe of that infuſion for the making of his Remedy, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto eight ounces of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> powdered and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled with four ounces of the Juyce of Fennel Root, and put into infuſion only for the ſpace of twelve hours.</p>
               <p>Sometimes inſtead of that Juyce he would employ the Juyce of Smallage Leaves, and at other times again that of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43006:36"/>Parſley, eſpecially in Tertian, and double Tertian Agues.</p>
               <p>In continued Feavers, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured us, that on the contrary he made uſe of the Juyces of the Plantin and Lettice, and in Malignant Feavers of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Scorſonera.</p>
               <p>In Quotidian Agues he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly beſprinkled his Powder with Vinegar of Squills, at the proportion of one ounce upon eight of the Jeſuits Powder, which he afterwards infuſed ſometimes in Rheniſh Wine, and ſometime in White Wine.</p>
               <p>For Quartan Agues he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Juyce of Pentaphyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum <hi>(Cinquefoil)</hi> and made his infuſion ſometimes in Spaniſh Wine.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:43006:36"/>
               <p>In ſlow and Hectick Feavers, he uſed the Juice of Colts Foot and Ground Ivie, and made his infuſion in one part of Wine, two parts of Barley Water, and one part of the Tincture of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>He followed that Practice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently for both Sexes, only with this difference, that with Women he ceaſed the uſe of his Remedy during their Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Prepared it for thoſe that were with Child, or in Child-Bed, in this manner; Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had wet his <hi>Quinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> with two ounces of the Juyce of Quinces, he infuſed it in equal parts of Wine and the Tincture of Roſes.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:43006:37"/>
               <p>In reſpect of Complicated Agues, he obſerved always to give his Febrifuge either in the Declenſion of the Fit, or in the beginning of the ſweating, but that circumſpection was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the more uſeleſs, that without conſidering, if theſe kinds of Feavers were the cauſe or the effects of other Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, he always bent himſelf wholly to the Cure of them; and it was by ſticking to that pernicious Maxim, that he er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo groſly in the Diſtemper of the Dauphin of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Feaver proceeding from Vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the weakneſs of his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, was encreaſed conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly by the uſe of his Febrifuge, and on the contrary ceaſed of it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43006:37"/>ſelf, when Remedies were only applied to correct the indiſpoſition that was the cauſe of it; not but that that Remedy hath ſome vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue againſt Vomiting and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Stomach which proceed from Crudities, Indigeſtion, and Relaxation of the Fibres of the Stomach; but it is abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to thoſe that are raiſed by a hot intemperature of the Viſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, and fomented by the irritati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of overflowing choler, as that of the Dauphins was.</p>
               <p>Hence one may judg how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it is to truſt the life and health of men, to the conduct of ſuch kind of People, whoſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is always too much limited, to reach beyond the general Rules and Directions contained in their
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43006:38"/>Receipts, and to deſcend into the exceptions that are indicated by ſound judgment, experience, and the Principles of a judicious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p>It is true, Sir <hi>Robert Talbor</hi> did not always obſerve the directions preſcribed in his Receipt, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time of the infuſion of <hi>Quinquina;</hi> but in that he was the more to be blamed: for beſides that, it is impoſſible that that Bark can in twelve; nay, even in twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four hours, impart all its bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and virtue to the Wine; there is ſtill much more time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to have the infuſion ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purated as it is to be wiſhed, that it may not be nauſeous, nor apt to cauſe obſtructions in the capil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary Veſſels, which hath cauſed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43006:38"/>troubleſome inconveniences to many who have been treated by that Emperick.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſame account it was, that in theſe late times thinking it beſt to give the Jeſuits Powder in Bolus, and by that means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive in ſome meaſure the antient and primitive method, which was to give it in ſubſtance; he hath often been the cauſe of many Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes far more pernicious than the Ague, which he pretended to Cure, the different Juyces where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he beſprinkled his Powder, being incapable to render it ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributive as not to ſtick in ſome part.</p>
               <p>But what preference ſoever the infuſions contained in the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Remedy may
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:43006:39"/>deſerve, it is ſtill true that ſeeing they cannot be ſafe but by the right uſe of them, it is no wonder if their effect hath ſometimes bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly correſponded to the underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of Sir <hi>Robert Talbor,</hi> ſince he gave them indifferently in all times of the Feaver, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſtopt in the beginning, without unpleaſing conſequences, that indiſpoſition, to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, being only a kind of Criſis excited by nature to force out of the Veſſels, Grude impure and ſuperfluous matters, which by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent cannot be ſtop too early, but that the ferments will lurk and remain in their <hi>Focus's</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſubſiſt in full force, which hath been the cauſe of thoſe dangerous relapſes, that firſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:43006:39"/>brought the Jeſuits Powder into contempt, which notwithſtanding is a moſt excellent Febrifuge.</p>
               <p>I do nevertheleſs acknowledg that there are ſome occaſions, wherein in the very beginning of the Feaver an urgent danger ſeems to demund a ſpeedy truce; but when, to have time to looae about us, we have capitulated with the Diſeaſe, we have procured an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that cannot withou great danger be abuſed, and whereof we cannot ſecure our ſelves the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, but by obſerving the Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims long ſince received, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſe of the Jeſuits Powder; that is to ſay, without ordering a Diet, Blood Letting, and eſpecially Purging, which by experience we know to be of indiſpenſable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:43006:40"/>
               <p>And now ſince I ſpeak of Purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I ought not to omit to ſay that it may be practiſed with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, before, or in the time, and after the uſe of the ſpecifick, obſerving the following Directions. When there is nothing that hinders from preparing the Body to receive the Jeſuits Powder, the eſſential part of that Preparation conſiſts in Purging Patients well, after they have been once or twice Let Blood, and that with relation to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the ſuperfluities and the degrees of repletion. When the action of the Ferments ſeems to reſiſt the operation of the Febri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and that therefore one is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to adminiſter Purgatives in the very time of uſing it, its force is to be augmented, or the Doſes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:43006:40"/>doubled, to the end that by the motion of the matters which are to be evacuated, the perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Blood be not encreaſed. In fine, when after we have done with the Remedy, we would by Purgatives prevent relapſes, it is better to give moderate and rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated Purges, than to give ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Doſes, and in leſs number.</p>
               <p>Futhermore, the ambition of Sir <hi>Robert Talbor</hi> having enclined him to extend the uſe of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy beyonds its efficacy, it is well known that he hath given it on divers occaſions for continued Feavers, wherein there was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intention nor remiſſion to be obſerved, which was always at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with tragical ſymptoms, and very often with death it ſelf;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43006:41"/>for that Remedy can never be ſucceſsfully given in thoſe kind of Feavers, unleſs when ſome mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Paroxyſms are obſerved, that they continued for ſeveral days, that the Patients have been Purged by all ways, and that they ſtand in need of a reſpite to recollect ſtrength, and ſo to relieve Nature, and give her time to perfect the Cure of the Diſtemper, which in vain ſhe ſtrove to ſurmount with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that aid and aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>He was guilty of a no ſmaller fault, in forcing, if I may ſay ſo, his Patients to drink Wine, and to eat ſolid Food during the whole time of continued Feavers, and in time of the Fit in Agues; for though in the abatement of the one, and the intermiſſion of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:43006:41"/>others, that kind of nouriſhment may back and fortifie the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Remedy; yet they conſiderably oppreſs the Patients, when Nature is taken up in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending her ſelf againſt the vigour of the Diſtemper that attacks her, and then it appears that the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and skill of a Learned and Experienced Phyſician, are at leaſt of as great relief on ſuch occaſions, as the moſt efficacious and ſalutory Medicines.</p>
               <p>I have no more to ſay to ſhew how little confidence we ought to have in ſuch kind of Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks, but that it is ſtrange that this man who hath preſcribed to us ſo many juyces, and ſuch like trifles about the compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Febrifuge, whereof
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:43006:42"/>the principle effect is only to be attributed to the Jeſuits Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſhould conceale the uſe that he made of <hi>Opium,</hi> whereof he many times added ſome drops of Tincture to this Febrifuge, which may be of great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage when it is given ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in over watchings, light headedneſs, and looſneſs, which are frequent ſymptoms in Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and always allayed by the virtue of that excellent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I hope the Reader will take in good part, that I deſcribe in this place a Febrifuge Opiat prepared with</hi> Quinquina, <hi>and afterward explain its effects, with relation to the Nature of Feavers and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:43006:42"/>
               <head>An Excellent Febrifuge.</head>
               <p>Take of the Jeſuits Powder, the Flowers or Leaf of leſſer Centaury ſubtilly Pulveriſed, and of Treacle, of each a like weight, make them into an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piat, of which the Patient twice a day ſhall take the weight of a Drachm and a half, during the ſpace of ſix days, drinking upon it a Glaſs of good Claret with Plantin or Bugloſs water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reflections upon the uſe of this Febrifuge.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The excellency of a Remedy is very often the cauſe why it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed. Antimony hath been in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:43006:43"/>our days a manifeſt inſtance of this, but the Jeſuits Powder, and the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Febrifuge continue us more plainly of the truth of it ſo ſoon as chance or induſtry hath diſcovered a ſecret for any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular diſtemper; the people lay hold on't as of a Publick Good, and apply it indifferently to all ſorts of evils; and if on ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion it ſucceed not, as it muſt unavoidably come to paſs, it is cried down with as much Zeal and Precipitance as it was brought in vogue. This is the fortune of all the new Febrifuges, having ſeen wonderful effects of them in ſome kinds of Feavers, men took them for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Remedies; but ſo ſoon as they found them produce bad conſequences in others for
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:43006:43"/>which they were not proper, it was then generally concluded that it was dangerous to make uſe of them. For this reaſon, that all ſcruples may be removed, which people may frame to themſelves in the uſe of this Febrifuge, I have thought it pertinent carefully to engage into the Nature of Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and to mark their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to obſerve thoſe which are ſubmitted to this Remedy, and thoſe to which it may prove pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial, and laſtly to prove with how much uſefulneſs it may be employed, when that is done with all care and neceſſary cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two motions are to be conceived in the blood, that of the whole
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:43006:44"/>which is the circulation, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the parts proceeding from its liquidity. A Feaver is a fermentation of the blood, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation is an irregular moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the inſenſible parts</hi> (motus inteſtinus partium inſenſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um) <hi>We muſt look into the cauſes of the regular motion of this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid body, that by the rule of contraries we may diſcover thoſe of the irregular motion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are two cauſes that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in the motion of the blood.</hi> 1. <hi>Its quantity, and the conſtantly equal force of the ſpirits, which are the immediate movers and impulſers of all the parts that compoſe this liquid maſs.</hi> 2. <hi>the juſt proportion of the ſame parts, as well in their
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:43006:44"/>quantity and quality, as in their ſcituation, that is to ſay, when the Sulphureous, Acide, Watry and Earthy corpuſcles, are not only in a laudable proportion as to quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but likewiſe are ſo well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted, and united together, that they no ways annoy one another, and are moved by the Spirits or Celeſtial matter that animates them, in a regular and uniform motion. As long as things are thus, it may be ſaid that the blood is in its Natural ſtate of Health, and to that end the Author of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath not only made our body tranſpirable, thereby to give vent to the too great quantity of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but hath alſo put in different places, Bowels and percolatories deſigned to filtrate the ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:43006:45"/>and exceeding parts, which might trouble the purety of that Liquor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From thence it may inferred that there are two immediate cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the fermentation of the blood, the firſt is the too great quantity, or the tor great motion of the ſpirits, which may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited by the heat of the Sun, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent exerciſe, watching, faſting, hot and ſpirituous nuriſhment; and the paſſions and perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the mind, and from thence it is that all Feavers</hi> Ephemerae <hi>or of one days continuance, and ſimple Synoches, which are the ſlighteſt of all, and may be cured by tranſpiration alone do ariſe, the ſecond is the mixture of irregular and fermentative corpuſcles</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:43006:45"/>non miſcibilium mixtio) <hi>which confounding the order and alliance of the parts of the Blood, raiſe a Sedition there, and deprave its motion. And of theſe Bodies ſome only raiſe a ſimple Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which at length may be governed and ſubdued by Nature, and the others being more Malignant and Venemous, cauſe Coagulations, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and Colliguations in the maſs of Blood, and can in no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be corrected. From the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe proceed all intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, erratick, and continued Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, which are called ſubintrant, and from the other ſpring Burning, Peſtilential, Malignant and ſpotted Feavers. It is now to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in what parts of our Body, and how theſe humours are produced.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:43006:46"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though I have ſaid that there are parts</hi> viſcera <hi>appointed for the ſeparation of the ſuperfluities of the blood, yet ſeeing they do not always diſcharge their functions aright, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through a fault in themſelves, or through the too great abundance of the ſame ſuperfluities, the ſame are hurried away by the rapidity of the circulation, as filth is carried away by the impetuous current of a River; but in the ſame manner as there happens a turning in that Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver where the water is ſtiller, and where all that filth turning ſlowly with the current ſtops; ſo theſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous bodies turn aſide by the coeliack Artery into the branches of the</hi> Vena Porta, <hi>where the Blood circulates more ſlowly, and which for that reaſon may be compared
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:43006:46"/>to a Lake or ſtanding Pool of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in reſpect of the other veſſels: there it is where wanting their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer agitation, they have the means of faſtening and uniting together, to produce obſtructions which are the primitive Cauſes of all Feavers of the ſecond order, and ſometimes, but ſeldome, of thoſe of the third, as I ſhall now illuſtrate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Blood cannot be long ſtopt in a place without being exaſperated and growing eager.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſpirits which are conſtantly in motion flie away, and carry with them firſt the more volatile parts, then the ſulphureous which blunted and edge of the Salts, and kept them as in fetters; which is the cauſe that theſe bodies having now nothing to ſtop their activity, break off and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:43006:47"/>diffuſe themſelves through the maſs of Blood to raiſe and ferment it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that being diſperſed and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the ſeroſity, they are expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the ordinary ways, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways do ſo adjuſt and accommodate themſelves with the other parts, that they diſturb their alliance and motion no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is nothing in Feavers but may be explained by this ſyſteme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The obſtruction and the ferment which remains in that part which is called the</hi> Focus, <hi>make the Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odick Fits and Paroxyſms, which are ſometimes quicker and ſometimes ſlower, according as the exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted humour is more groſs or more ſubtile: the duplicity of</hi> Focus's <hi>or Magazines make the double inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittent Feavers. In a word there
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:43006:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>happen ſometimes ſo many of theſe neſts, that giving no reſpite, they cauſe continued Feavers, which may be called ſubintrants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But it ſometimes happens that theſe acid Salts, whether through their their too long continuance in a place, or by an exceſſive heat of the entralls, acquire a pretty violent degree of corroſion, and are exalted to that height as to become venemous enough for ſpoiling, and wholly rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the oeconomy of the blood, and cauſing thoſe Feavers which by a general name are called</hi> Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; <hi>but ſince the more common cauſe of theſe Feavers, are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Salts diffuſed through the Air which we breath, or lurking in the Food we eat, and that it is rare that our Natural heat which
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:43006:48"/>is mild, ſhould produce in our Bodies that which the moſt violent fire of Chymiſts can hardly perform in their Veſſels; I ſaid it was the leſs ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſes of thoſe kinds of Feavers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Having laid down theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, I ſay that this Remedy is uſeleſs for the firſt, and dangerous for the third kind of Feavers; uſeleſs for the firſt, becauſe they are commonly cured of themſelves, and dangerous for the third, becauſe a venemous Body, and ſuch as in no ways can be ſubdued nor corrected ought never to be fixed; on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary it ought with all expedition to be driven out by ſweats, or by other ways of evacuation: But I main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that this Remedy anſwers all the indications that we can have for the Cure of thoſe of the ſecond order.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:43006:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Explication which I have given of theſe Feavers, which by a general name may be called inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittent, furniſhes me with four indications for their Cure.</hi> 1. <hi>To ſtop the Fermentation of the Blood.</hi> 2. <hi>To fix and correct the Acid which is the cauſe of it.</hi> 3. <hi>To diſſolve, attenuate and drive out by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ways of evacuation the groſs humours that make obſtructions.</hi> 4. <hi>And laſtly to repair the loſs of the Sulphureous and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nctuous Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles which ſweetened the Blood, and which are evaporated by its offerveſcencie.</hi> 1. <hi>The feaveriſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullition of the Blood is ſufficiently ſtopt by the terreſtrial and aſtringent parts of the</hi> Quinquina <hi>or</hi> Jeſuits Powder, <hi>and by the leſſer Centau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and the Opium that enters the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:43006:49"/>compoſition of the Treacle.</hi> 2. <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many fair experiments, we have no cauſe to doubt, but that the fixed Salt of the</hi> Quinquina <hi>is the true corrective of the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Acid of the Feaver.</hi> 3. <hi>Of all the ingredients that enter the compoſition of Treacle, there is none but drives out by ſweating and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine the impurities of the Blood. Laſtly we may be eaſily perſuaded that the leſſer Centaury is moſt proper for reſtoring the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureous parts of the Blood which have been diſſipated in the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if we conſider its wonderful virtue in conſolidating of wounds; and if we obſerve that the reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſeparated parts, is only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by a Balſamick and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sulpher wherewith that Plant
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:43006:49"/>abounds. The wine that is given immediately after contributes much alſo to that effect, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when the activity of its ſpirits is checked by the mixture of the Plant in water, which on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſon I ſhould prefer before that of Bugloſs. I pretend not for all this to exclude the general and common remedies of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. Nay, I maintain, that in the beginning once or twice Blood-letting, according to the ſtrength and repletion of the Patient are neceſſary, as well for facilitating the circulation of the blood, as for remedying the pains of the head, and oppreſſions that Blood ſwelling in the fermentation, may cauſe in paſſing through the capillary veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the Brain and Lungs. This
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:43006:50"/>Remedy is not to be given till firſt by a diſſolution of</hi> Caſſia <hi>or</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicum, <hi>the excrements of the lower region, which may trouble its operation, be evacuated. And laſtly, ſeeing the blood, like other Liquors in their ebullition, drives always towards the Meſentery a great many impure and foeculent parts like a ſcum, it is neceſſary in the declenſion of the evil to purge them out, if one would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent relapſes, and ſometimes more troubleſome conſequences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing it appears by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks of the Kings chief Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, and by the foregoing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions, that Opium may uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be added to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and other Febrifuges of the ſame Nature; I make no
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:43006:50"/>doubt but that you will Read with pleaſure the Natural Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of that excellent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Hiſtory of Opium.</head>
               <p>OPium by moſt of the Eaſtern people is ſtill named <hi>Offium,</hi> in imitation of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who commonly change <hi>p.</hi> into an <hi>f.</hi> it is the thickned juyce of the <hi>Indian</hi> Poppy. <hi>Garrias du Jardin,</hi> ſaith that theſe Heads are big enough to contain four Ounces and a half. Our Poppies yield alſo a juyce, which being thickned may paſs for a kind of Opium; but it hath not the efficacy of that which is brought from hot
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:43006:51"/>Countries. The Author of the <hi>Poor mans Phyſician,</hi> propoſes a very eaſie preparation of it, he would have us pound the Heads of our Poppies about the end of <hi>May,</hi> then put them in digeſtion in White Wine for the ſpace of fifteen days, and afterwards by evaporation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the digeſted liquor into a due conſiſtency.</p>
               <p>The true <hi>Indian</hi> Opium comes from the Eaſtern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trys, according to the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Garrias du Jardin,</hi> and <hi>Criſtopher de la Coſte.</hi> The Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies from which it is taken grow commonly enough in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and therefore Merchands bring much of it from <hi>Grand Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro;</hi> this is in greateſt eſteem,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:43006:51"/>and is called Thebaick Opium.</p>
               <p>Not to mention the Opium that may be made of the Poppies of <hi>Longuedoc</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> nor of that which is made in <hi>Italy,</hi> we may divide into three kinds that which is brought us from the <hi>Indies;</hi> for there is one ſort of it White, which the <hi>Indians</hi> keep for their own uſe, and which is only drawn out by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation, having made inciſion in the Heads of the Poppies; and it is to this properly that the Antients gave the name of Opium; for as to the ſecond kind which is black, and which is extracted only by expreſſion, they called it <hi>Maeconium;</hi> the third ſort is Yellowiſh and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſophiſticated with the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:43006:52"/>juyce of <hi>Glaucium,</hi> which is an Herb whoſe Leaves reſemble thoſe of horned Poppy, and are bitter and of an evil ſmell: that Sophiſtication is diſcovered by diſſolving that kind of Opium in ſome Liquor; for becauſe of that juice of <hi>Glaucium</hi> which is Yellow, it looks like the Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Saffron.</p>
               <p>The good <hi>Maeconium,</hi> that is ſay Opium of the ſecond kind ought to be black, bitter, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle biting to the taſte, of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant ſmell, pure, ſolid, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous, inflammable, and ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within when it is newly broken.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Europe</hi> it is only uſed in Phyſick, and moſt part of our Phyſicians are ſo ſcrupulous in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:43006:52"/>uſing it, that they ſeem to look upon it as a moſt dangerous Poyſon, though it be indeed one of the ſafeſt and moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful of all our Medicines; but the <hi>Africans</hi> and <hi>Aſians</hi> make extraordinory great uſe of it both in Health and Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for moſt of them take it dayly in ſo large a Doſe, that it amounts commonly to forty or fifty Grains, and ſomtimes alſo to four or five Drachms, at leaſt if we believe <hi>Garrias du Jardin;</hi> and which is more ſtrange, when they leave off taking of it they are in danger of death, unleſs they drink Wine, which their Religion forbids: the reaſon of that cuſtome is, becauſe thereby
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:43006:53"/>they find themſelves more ſtrong and vigorous, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that the <hi>Turks</hi> never fail to take of it in a great Doſe, when they are going to charge an Enemy, or Attack a place.</p>
               <p>Howſoevever it be, ſeeing pain is the cruelleſt Enemy that men have; ſo there is nothing they ought to eſteem more than what eaſes them of it; and therefore ſome have called O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium a Divine Medicine; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it charms the moſt vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pain, by procuring a ſoft and ſweet ſleep, and does ſo quiet and ſtill the impetuous motion of the irritated ſpirits and exalted fiery Corpuſcles, that it ſtops the operation of all thoſe ſharp and biting
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:43006:53"/>juyces that depended thereupon.</p>
               <p>The Ancients in regard of theſe admirable effects, believed that the virtue of Opium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted only in fixation, which could not proceed but from a cold quality; in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as they believed that all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions depended on heat. The Moderns, on the contrary, have obſerved that becauſe of the Countries from whence it comes, its pierceing ſmell, and how eaſily it is diſſolved in the Spirit of Wine, it muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be Reſinous, Sulphureous and conſequently of the Nature of thoſe mixts to which a hot quality is aſſigned: In a word, ſome of the lateſt Authors who have written of it to reconcile
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:43006:54"/>thoſe two Opinions, ſay that there are two ſubſtances in it, the one cold, which renders it ſtupefactive, and the other hot, which gives it a requiſite volati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to convey it to the Brain; but ſeeing neither the one nor the other are in the right, as not having grounded their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the true Nature of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium, that is to ſay, with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the number, quality and quantity of the Elementary principles that enter into its compoſition; we muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity take another courſe in explaining more exactly the properties of that rare Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
               <p>For that end, ſeeing Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um is of the kind of bitter Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decines,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:43006:54"/>it would ſeem that I ſhould begin by an enquiry into the principles of bitterneſs; but ſeeing I have been large enough on that ſubject, when I treated of the Nature of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> I think it more pertinent to refer the Reader to that place; than here to make repetitions (which doubtleſs would be as unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant as uſeleſs) concerning the general Doctrine of bitter things.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs that I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into the particular Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Opium, that is to ſay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the enumeration of thoſe things that diſtinguiſh it from other bitter mixts, I confeſs that that diſtinction being founded upon this, that it is both fixative
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:43006:55"/>and by conſequence Febrifugrous, Somniferous, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent <hi>Anodin;</hi> we muſt enquire in what manner it acts upon the blood and ſpirits in producing ſuch wonderful effects: for a more clear notion of this, it is to be obſerved, that the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular motion of the parts of the blood, wherein its liquidity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, becomes of neceſſity a hinderance to that of the whole maſs, when it is grown irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar by fermentative cauſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame parts being then violently agitated and every way diſperſed, they juſtle irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly one upon another, and ſo in ſome manner reſiſt the action of the chief movers of the blood, that cauſes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:43006:55"/>of its circulary mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which according as it is more or leſs conſiderable, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Feaver, over watching, particular inflamations, and the extravaſation of ſharp and bite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juyces, that produce all kinds of pain.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing that ſome depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation may be rectified by bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, as I have demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted when I ſpoke of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> and that if amongſt all mixts of that quality, thoſe that are too week acting but imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and thoſe that are too ſtrong irritating many times the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in ſtead of fixing them, ſuch as are of a moderate force are of greature virtue than others; it is not ſtrange if Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:43006:56"/>which is but moderately bitter, ſo efficaciouſly reſtore to the blood the uniformity of its motion, and by conſequent that pleaſant tranquility that charms us a ſleep and eaſes our pains.</p>
               <p>But in as much as there are inflamations or (if one may ſay ſo) Feavers that are peculiar to every part of the body, and that becauſe of diſquietneſs and application to Study and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Head is frequently ſubject to ſuch, which cauſe watchings, and which ſeem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to proceed from the irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirits, than the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation of the motion of the blood, it muſt indeed be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that Opium which ſo
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:43006:56"/>quickly rectifies that diſorder, hath ſome property which is not common to other bitter Medecines; but this is not hard to be explained; for ſuppoſing that all, or almoſt all the drogues of that quality, have the virtue to rally, reunite and fix the parts of the Liquors of our body, in which they are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed; it is ſufficient that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um above all other bitter Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines have as many volatile parts as are needful to make thoſe parts wherein its bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and virtue of fixing liquids does conſiſt, to be conveighed from the Stomach to the Brain, that by means of that Sublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they may have occaſion of acting upon the extravaſated
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:43006:57"/>Liquors, and conſequently upon thoſe that are appointed for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and hindering the diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Animal Spirits, whoſe impetuous motion cauſes watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as their calm and ſtillneſs produces ſleep.</p>
               <p>But to ſpeak ſomewhat more intelligibly upon this Subject, I would have it obſerved in the firſt place, that the continual emiſſion of Animal Spirits into all the Nerves, and by conſequence into thoſe that conſtitute the organs of the ſenſes producing that ſtate of Body, which we call <hi>being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake,</hi> and wherein the Body is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of all the Functions that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on the Will; the diſſipation of the ſame Spirits, and every thing that hinders their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:43006:57"/>are the cauſes or ſleep; which may be defined a diſpoſition wherein the external ſenſes are ſo dulled, that they are incapable of the perceptions which they give to the mind, and wherein all the other parts of the Body are weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, relaxated and improper for thoſe voluntary actions, to which Nature hath deſtin'd them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for ſuch never ſleep ſound who have their eyes open, ſpeak, walk, or perform thoſe functions aſleep, which ſeem to depend on the Will, ſince they ſuppoſe the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſtrength, and in a word the motion of the Nerves, which can only be referred to the motion of the Spirits, wherewith they are then poſſeſſed.</p>
               <p>This being ſuppoſed, it will not
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:43006:58"/>be hard to conceive why one falls naturally aſleep after Labour and Travel, and after long Watching; for ſeeing thoſe things diſſipate many Spirits, they are at length too few to fill all the Nerves, to ſupport the Body, and to render it fit for ſanſation and motion, inſomuch that it neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains as without motion and ſenſe, until the Blood being depurated and ſubtilized by its continual cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, diſcharges into the Brain a ſufficient quantity of Spirits to make up the loſs of the former diſſipation.</p>
               <p>With the ſame facility may be given the reaſon of dullneſs which is ſo common during the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of Victuals; for ſeeing that cannot be performed without the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:43006:58"/>elevation of Vapours into the Brain, which entangle the Spirits, and make a kind of obſtruction in the Orifices of the Nerves, it is no wonder if the extremities of the Body droop, and be weak and dull, ſince they cannot be ſtrong and proper for action, unleſs they have a continual and abundant ſupply of Spirits.</p>
               <p>This laſt Obſervation will be very uſeful to confirm the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation that I have given of ſleep which is procured by <hi>Opium,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its Volatile and Vaporous parts are much more powerful than thoſe that proceed from the digeſtion of Victuals, whether for fixing of the humours and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, or for obſtructing the Nerves by which they are diſtributed
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:43006:59"/>through all the parts of the Body.</p>
               <p>Since then <hi>Opium</hi> procures ſleep by the power that it hath to ſtop the Spirits in the Brain, it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follows that it muſt aſſwage pain, ſuſpend preternatural eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuations, and ſtop all kinds of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, ſeeing theſe indiſpoſitions depend naturally upon the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the Juyce, and that the Spirits flowing no more towards the part where it happens, it muſt of neceſſity diminiſh as the Spirits that are contained in the fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted matter are diſſipated, and wholly ceaſe, when the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are entirely diſperſed, becauſe there comes no new ſupplies, and the ſubſtances that are deſtitute of the ſame, ferment no more, as experience confirms in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:43006:59"/>of cold abſceſſes and painleſs tumors.</p>
               <p>Though this explanation of the effects of <hi>Opium</hi> be very plain, yet it makes it evidently enough appear why it is ſo great a relief in watchings, frenſie, inveterate and contumacious pains of the Head, Gonvulſions, Aſthma's, Coughs, loſs of Blood, Diſſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Colicks, Fluxes and Looſneſs, Gonorheas, and generally in all Diſeaſes which are cauſed and continued by ſharp, corrupt and fermentative Juyces.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, when <hi>Opium</hi> is prepared with Aromatick and Cordial Medicines, it is called <hi>Laudanum;</hi> this Preparation is made with deſign to correct its imaginary coldneſs, and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:43006:60"/>needleſs. It may be given then in ſubſtance without any ſcruple or ceremony, unleſs one had rather prepare it according to the advice of the Poor Mans Phyſician; which conſiſts in dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it well, that the impure Sulphers may exhale, and then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving it in roſe Vinegar, to Cure it of its bad ſmell, and leſſen its Volatility; but its beſt Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is barely to diſſolve it in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine, that it may be given by way of a Tincture, as the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Phyſitian uſed to do, and is very convenient.</p>
               <p>Opiats have drawn their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Name from Opium, and I cannot tell why they have given the Name of Confection to Orvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etan, Treacle and Mithridate,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:43006:60"/>whereof it is an Ingredient; and on the contrary, have given that of Opium to many Compoſitions into which it enters not; for it is certainly the moſt efficacious of all Antidotes, and I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by experience, that <hi>Venice Treacle</hi> is only more excellent than others, becauſe it contains Opium in a greater quantity.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, that if it were pure and without all falſification, it would cauſe blindneſs; but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that, there is no more requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red than only to give it in the neceſſary Doſe for the effect which we expect from it: beſides, the Doſe wherein we give that which is brought to us, being always proportionable to that I have been ſpeaking of, it would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:43006:61"/>that that accident ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to thoſe to whom it is given, if it were true that it is capable to cauſe it. To conclude, they who pretend that it ought to be ranked among Poyſons, ſhould confeſs that it kills not but when a bad uſe is made of it; and that ſo there is no more Poyſon in it, than in the beſt Medicines: and I dare be bold to ſay, that our very Food, of which Bread is he moſt innocent, being taken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure, may cauſe a Surfeit, and Mortal Suffocation.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:43006:61"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
